Robert Hillyer Papers
Robert Hillyer Papers
- Literary correspondence
  - Smith, Harrison, 1949-1950; 6 Letters (Box 5)
    18 Apr. 1949 - TLS Mentions correspondence with Leonie Adams and reassures Hillyer that The Saturday Review of Literature is willing to back Hillyer's articles concerning The Fellows of American Letters.
    21 Apr. 1949 - TLS Differs with Hillyer's approach to article on The Fellows of American Letters of The Library of Congress and makes it clear that these are to create a cause celebre.
    2 May 1949 - TLS Praises Hillyer's article on The Fellows of American Letters but differs with concluding paragraph calling for punishment; suggests alternative attitudes.
    3 May 1949 - TLS Analyzes Luther Evans attitude towards Hillyer's articles and towards the Fellows.
    15 Jun. 1949 - ALS Returns personal letters praising Hillyer's articles.
    30 Aug. 1950 - ALS Describes health.
  - Snow, Wilbur, undated; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    Undated - ALS Mentions coming lecture of T. S. Eliot at Harvard.
  - Pencer, Theodore, 1941; 1948,; 1961; 3 Letters (Box 5)
    30 Oct. 1941 - ALS Thanks Hillyer for laudatory introduction given Spencer.
    3 Jan. 1948 - ALS Thanks Hillyer for suggestions.
    18 Dec. 1961 - TLS Thanks Hillyer profusely for his praise of novel and explains in detail the areas in which he disagrees with Hillyer.
  - Speyer, Leonora, 1938-1939; 1949; 11 Letters, 2 Typescript Poems (Box 5)
    Undated - Typed signed copy of author's poem "Il miglior fabbro."
    Undated - Typed signed copy of author's poem "Again The Swan."
    14 Apr. - ALS
    12 May. - ALS
    28 Apr. 1938 - TLS Discusses editorial and tells of arrangement to supply Hillyer with reprints of same.
    28 Mar. 1939 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's sonnet "In Time of Mistrust."
    12 Jun. 1949 - TLS Sends copy of letter to William Benet on Hillyer's The Saturday Review of Literature article.
    16 Jun. 1949 - ALS Praises further Hillyer's The Saturday Review of Literature.
    21 Jun. 1949 - ALS Reports William Benet's refusal to print Speyer’s letter in his column "Phoenix Nest" due to space limitations.
    22 Jun. 1949 - ALS Further comments on Hillyer's The Saturday Review of Literature articles; encloses copy of letter to The Saturday Review of Literature on subject.
    20 Aug. 1949 - ALS
    20 Oct. 1949 - ALS
    8 Nov. 1949 - ALS Discusses the health of Edna St. Vincent Millay and the possibility of awarding her the Academy prize.
  - Stuart, Jesse, 1944; 1961; 4 Letters (Box 5)
    18 Dec. 1944 - TLS Mentions Hillyer's review "Among the New Volumes of Verse" in the New York Times which praised Album of Destiny.
    31 Mar. 1961 - ALS Discusses Hillyer's In Pursuit of Poetry and mentions award from The American Academy of Poets.
    25 May 1961 - ALS Praises Hillyer at length for his stand on T. S. Eliot and Ezra Pound.
    19 Jul. 1961 - ALS Comments on Hillyer's abilities as poet and critic and discusses the influence of Hillyer, Eliot and Pound on American poetry.
  - Sullivan, A. M., 1956; 1958-1959,; 1961; 5 Letters (Box 5)
    12 Jan. 1956 - ALS Asks permission to quote from Hillyer's article on General Gallieni and the taxis of Paris.
    14 Oct. 1958 - TLS
    24 Apr. 1959 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's "Eppur Si Muove" and encloses author's poem on internal problems of Poetry Society of America.
    31 Jan. 1961 - TLS Encloses author's "Inauguration Poem" written for John F. Kennedy.
  - Sullivan, Frank, 1938; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    2 Mar. 1938 - ALS Discusses music.
  - Tadin, Boris, 1948-1949; 8 Letters (Box 5)
    20 Apr. 1948 - TLS
    9 Jun. 1948 - ALS Describes Paris and post-war conditions there.
    28 Jun. 1948 - ALS
    15 Jun. 1948 - ALS Thanks Hillyer for his efforts on his behalf to obtain an advance; discusses travel difficulties.
    24 Jun. 1948 - ALS Discusses European trip and possibility of obtaining a position at Harvard in an effort to combat "acrobatic school of poetry."
    13 Jul. 1948 - TLS Discusses state of war in Israel and describes air alerts and bombing procedures of Egyptians.
    24 Aug. 1948 - TLS Discusses health and conditions affecting it.
    9 Jun. 1949 - TLS Compliments Hillyer on his article "Treason's Strange Fruit."
  - Taggard, Genevieve, undated; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    Undated - ALS Discusses arrangements for Hillyer's participation in Alumnae Week-End Conference on Emily Dickinson; encloses Program.
  - Tarkington, Booth, 1938-1939; 3 Letters (Box 5)
    5 Feb. 1938 - TLS Mentions Hillyer's entry into the National Institute of Arts and Letters and comments on Hillyer's recent attack as an Old Guardsman by "the Marx-Matisse-Joyce contingent."
    28 Apr. 1938 - TLS Discusses his editorial written for Wythe Williams.
    28 Mar. 1939 - TLS Thanks Hillyer for sending him copy of "In Time of Mistrust" and for inscribing it.
  - Tate, Allen, 1938; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    23 Feb. 1938 - ALS Comments on the Morris Gray Lecture at Harvard.
  - Teller, Walter Magnes, 1958-1959; 1961; 8 Letters (Box 5)
    3 Apr. 1958 - TLS Expresses gratification at Hillyer's interest in biography of Captain Slocum; requests permission to quote Hillyer on Slocum in article enclosed.
    21 Apr. 1958 - TLS Mentions projected publication of The Voyages of Joshua Slocum.
    6 Oct. 1958 - TLS Hopes Hillyer will review The Voyages of Joshua Slocum.
    1 Dec. 1958 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's review of The Voyages of Joshua Slocum for the New York Times.
    8 Mar. 1959 - TLS Thanks Hillyer for sending The Lookout.
    31 Jan. 1961 - TLS Mentions Hillyer's poem "Moo," In Pursuit of Poetry, and encloses copy of author's Five Sea Captains.
    21 Feb. 1961 - TLS
    23 Mar. 1961 - TLS Praises Hillyer's In Pursuit of Poetry.
  - Thayer, Scofield, 1923; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    31 Oct. 1923 - TLS Encloses check for purchase of Hillyer's sonnet "Tell me, from what dark, smoky, terminal."
  - Todd, Mabel Loomis, 1923; undated; 1 Letter, 1 Card (Box 5)
    Undated - Christmas Card, Signed.
    5 Oct. 1923 - TLS Praises Hillyer's article on Emily Dickinson and invites him to discuss her at some later date.
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1929-1930; 1934-1936,; 1940-1942,; 1947; 18 Letters, 5 Cards (Box 5)
    11 Aug. - Signed Card.
    Undated - Signed Card. Mentions projected high school textbook.
    Undated - TLS Discusses author's inclusion of Hillyer's "A Letter to Robert Frost" and "The Assassination" in revision of anthology of Modern American Poetry.
    10 Jun. 1929 - TLS Discusses inclusion of Hillyer's "So Soft in the Hemlock Wood," "August Afternoon in a Drowse," and "Prothalamion" in Modern American Poetry.
    15 Jun. 1929 - ALS Confirms inclusion of Hillyer's "So Soft in the Hemlock Wood," now entitled "Pastoral," and part of Hillyer's "Prothalamion" in anthology.
    9 Sept. 1930 - ALS
    24 Oct. 1930 - ALS Comments on Hillyer's The Gates of the Compass.
    19 Feb. 1934 - TLS Agrees to read manuscript of Hillyer protégé and discusses literary work on poetry.
    18 Apr. 1934 - TLS Mentions Hillyer's loss of house in Pomfret.
    22 May 1934 - TLS Analyzes and comments at length on work of Hillyer's protégé.
    15 Jul. 1935 - TLS Discusses inclusion of Hillyer's poem "Variations on a Theme" in projected work.
    14 Aug. 1935 - TLS Discusses inclusion of Robert Bridge's work in anthology; comments on inclusion of Santayana.
    18 Apr. 1936 - TLS Discusses difficulties encountered in creating anthology and comments on Carl Sandburg.
    25 Apr. 1941 - TLS Discusses revision of anthology of Modern American Poetry and mentions inclusion of Hillyer's "The Assassination."
    17 May 1941 - TLS Mentions Viking prospectus and discusses work in progress; mentions A Treasury of the World's Great Poems.
    12 Jun. 1941 - TLS Discusses Hillyer poems to be included in anthology.
    11 Jul. 1941 - TLS Comments on neglect of Hillyer's rights by Random House.
    19 Jun. 1941 - Signed Card. Confirms inclusion of Hillyer's "A Letter to Robert Frost" in anthology.
    20 Mar. 1942 - Signed Card.
    4 Apr. 1947 - TLS Questions Hillyer about poet Edward Taylor; envelope bears holograph comments by Hillyer.
    30 Apr. 1947 - TLS Describes author's work on Edward Taylor for anthology.
    29 Oct. 1947 - TLS Mention's Untermeyer's recent loss, Hillyer's Poems for Music, and The New England Poets.
  - Van Den Arend, Fred, 1912; 1914; 4 Letters (Box 5)
    29 Jun. 1912 - ALS A facetious letter discussing plans for entering Harvard; discusses their friendship.
    4 Jul. 1912 - ALS Further discusses friendship of Hillyer and author.
    3 Aug. 1912 - ALS
    11 Sept. 1914 - ALS Describes summer activities and discusses reopening of school.
  - Van Doren, Mark, 1938; 1940,; 1947,; 1949,; 1953; 7 Letters (Box 5)
    21 Oct. 1938 - ALS
    7 May 1940 - ALS
    5 Oct. 1947 - ALS Comments on Hillyer's review of author's book in the New York Times Book Review.
    9 May 1949 - ALS
    12 Jan. 1949 - ALS
    15 Jan. 1949 - ALS
    1 Nov. 1953 - ALS
  - Venini, Paolo, 1958; 1 Letter, 1 Card (Box 5)
    10 Oct. 1958 - Signed Card.
    18 Nov. 1958 - ALS
  - Viereck, Peter, 1948-1950; 1953,; 1961,; undated; 13 Letters (Box 5)
    Undated - Typescript copies of new poems with holograph greeting.
    29 Mar. - TLS Discusses work in Conservatism Revisited and comments on The Death of Captain Nemo.
    19 Jul. - TLS Discusses Hillyer's attack on Ezra Pound and T. S. Eliot and compares attitudes towards them; comments on The Death of Captain Nemo.
    13 Jan. 1948 - TLS Congratulates Hillyer on election to presidency of Poetry Society of America and mentions inclusion in Louis Untermeyer's anthology.
    20 Oct. 1948 - TLS Appreciation of Hillyer's comments on book; requests Hillyer to review it if possible.
    17 Nov. 1949 - TLS Discusses at length the Bollingen Award to Ezra Pound; mentions author's Conservatism Revisited.
    4 May 1950 - TLS Disagrees at great length with some of Hillyer's attitudes towards the Bollingen Award, T. S. Eliot; points out areas of agreement on Ezra Pound.
    6 Jun. 1950 - TLS Mentions participation as judges in Hopwood Poetry contest and comments on literary work in progress.
    1 Jul. 1950 - TLS Mentions and describes work in progress.
    8 Jun. 1953 - Typescript copy of "Same Refrains at the River Charles" with holograph greeting. Typescript copy of comment on poem "Same Refrains at the River Charles" with holograph greeting. Tearsheet of poem "Which of us Two?" with holograph greeting.
    25 May 1961 - Copy; Praises Hillyer's Collected Poems to Alfred A. Knopf and requests that Copy; be sent on to Hillyer.
  - Vijayatunga, J., 1957; 1961-1962; 4 Letters (Box 5)
    8 Jun. 1957 - ALS Discusses forthcoming publication of Homage to the Buddha including poem by Hillyer.
    7 Jul. 1961 - TLS Discusses use of a Hillyer poem in book.
    Undated [1961] - TLS Condolences to Mrs. Hillyer.
    9 Jan. 1962 - TLS Condolences to Mrs. Hillyer.
  - Waters, Edward N., 1959; 2 Letters (Box 5)
    24 Feb. 1959 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's manuscript of Liszt song "Ihr Glocken von Marling."
    25 Feb. 1959 - TLS Encloses photostatic negative of Liszt manuscript.
  - Weeks, Edward, 1951; 1958-1962; 9 Letters (Box 5)
    Oct. 1951 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's poem "Through the Drift of Years."
    2 Sept. 1958 - TLS Comments on collaboration of Donald Adams and Hollister to write book on Charles Townsend Copeland; inquires about speech of Hillyer.
    24 Jun. 1959 - TLS Offers to help Hillyer secure a Mellon Professorship at University of Pittsburgh; mentions omission of Hillyer's birth poem from June issue of The Atlantic.
    4 Apr. 1960 - TLS Mentions forthcoming publication of Hillyer's Collected Poems.
    15 Jun. 1961 - TLS
    23 Oct. 1961 - TLS Comments on Hillyer's projected memoirs, and possibility of finding a retreat in the Bahamas.
    1 Jan. 1962 - ALS Condolences to Mrs. Hillyer.
    31 Jan. 1962 - TLS Returns to Mrs. Hillyer unpublished Hillyer poem "Song."
    1 Mar. 1962 - TLS Letter to Edmund Wilson concerning an excerpt from Hillyer's projected memoirs.
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1958; 1960-1961; 2 Letters, 3 Cards (Box 5)
    14 Feb. 1958 - ALS Inquires about the tax status of Borestone Mountain Poetry Awards.
    3 Aug. 1960 - Signed Card. Agrees to vote for Hillyer's candidate for Academy Fellowship under certain conditions; praises Hillyer's poem "Muffled Gong."
    23 Apr. 1961 - Signed Card. Thanks Hillyer for choosing Wheelock as recipient of Quarterly Award of The Lyric.
    15 Sept. 1961 - Signed Card. Thanks Hillyer for criticizing poem "The Gardener."
    27 Dec. 1961 - ALS Condolences to Mrs. Hillyer.
  - Wilbur, Richard, 1961; 1 Letter, 1 Card (Box 5)
    28 Jan. 1961 - Signed Card. Mentions unnamed work in progress.
    10 Dec. 1961 - ALS Appreciation of Hillyer's unnamed book with special reference to poem "Nocturne."
  - Wilder, Thornton, undated; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    Undated - ALS A letter of reference to Hillyer concerning a student.
  - Winters, Yvor, 1934; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    20 Aug. 1934 - ALS Letter of introduction for student.
  - Wood, Peggy, 1941; 1 Letter (Box 5)
    23 Oct. 1941 - ALS Requests holograph copy of Hillyer's poem "Moo."
  - Wortman, Doris, 1956; 1958,; 1962; 8 Letters (Box 5)
    1 Mar. 1956 - TLS Recounts life.
    26 Mar. 1956 - TLS Discusses Hillyer's background.
    7 Jun. 1956 - TLS Discusses word puzzles and attitudes of editors towards them.
    5 Jul. 1956 - TLS Discusses details of projected visit by the Hillyers.
    12 Aug. 1956 - TLS
    29 Aug. 1956 - TLS
    28 Oct. 1958 - TLS
    3 Jan. 1962 - TLS Condolences to Mrs. Hillyer.
  - Wright, Cuthbert, 1923-1924; undated; 3 letters (Box 5)
    Undated - TL
    5 Feb. 1923 - ALS
    Dec. 1924 - ALS
  - Zaturenska, Marya, 1921; 1941,; 1943-1949,; 1953,; undated; 30 Letters, 2 Cards (Box 5)
    Undated - Signed Card. Discusses attitudes of new young poets and describes a party given by Partisan Review.
    Undated - ALS Comments on various literary awards and discusses poetry readings.
    Undated - ALS Comments on Hillyer's "Prothalamion," Harriet Monroe, Horace Gregory, and mentions personal difficulties.
    Undated - ALS Discusses personal matters.
    10 Mar. 1921 - ALS Appreciates Hillyer's The Five Books of Youth, mentions Hillyer's aunt, and comments on The Poetry Society of America.
    4 May 1921 - ALS Comments on Vachel Lindsay.
    7 Feb. 1941 - TLS Discusses forthcoming publications of author and Horace Gregory and mentions W. H. Auden, Theodore Spender, Louis MacNiece, and Richard Blackmur.
    14 Mar. 1941 - ALS Comments on Richard Blackmur, the war, and mentions author's and Horace Gregory's new books.
    30 Nov. 1943 - ALS Thanks Hillyer for his efforts, in conjunction with Louis Untermeyer, to obtain Academy grant.
    29 Jan. 1944 - ALS Discusses recent attacks on Hillyer with special comment on Allen Tate.
    21 Mar. 1944 - ALS Comments on Yeats, discusses personal life, mentions Dunstan Thompson’s novel.
    3 May 1944 - ALS Discusses influence of California on certain authors and comments on Horace Gregory, Theodore Spenser, Theodore Morrison and Horace Gregory's book The Shield of Achilles.
    24 Aug. 1944 - ALS Comments on author's new book of poetry and discusses Karl Shapiro at length.
    25 Oct. 1944 - ALS Discusses author's new book and the critical attacks on it, with comments on Louise Bogan and William Carlos Williams.
    1 May 1945 - ALS Praises Hillyer's article on Emily Dickinson
    14 May 1945 - ALS Comments on Hillyer's residence in Greenwich Village and discusses author's and Horace Gregory's forthcoming book.
    27 Jan. 1946 - ALS Discusses author's and Horace Gregory's forthcoming book A History of American Poetry 1900 - 1940.
    11 Nov. 1946 - ALS Discusses attacks on author's and Horace Gregory's book with special mention of Delmore Schwartz.
    26 Nov. 1946 - ALS Mentions forthcoming Hillyer review of author's and Horace Gregory's book and recounts story about Randall Jarrell.
    25 Feb. 1947 - ALS Mentions projected book on Christina Rossetti and comments on Hillyer's projected collection of poems.
    7 May 1947 - ALS Mentions further attacks on author's book with extended comment on books by Mary Colum and Samuel Putnam.
    1 Sept. 1947 - ALS Criticizes Hillyer's new book Poems for Music.
    25 Sept. 1947 - ALS Mentions projected review of Hillyer's book.
    24 Dec. 1947 - ALS Discusses the current reputation of various poets including e.e. cummings, W. H. Auden, Stephen Spender.
    19 Feb. 1948 - ALS Describes critic-poet party given by Stephen Spender.
    5 Mar. 1948 - ALS Comments on Marianne Moore, David Morton, and Allen Tate.
    14 Apr. 1948 - ALS Discusses Hillyer's life and work and describes Louise Nicholls; mentions Mary Colum.
    1 Aug. 1949 - ALS Discusses projected Hillyer poem The Death of Captain Nemo, and mentions work on Christina Rossetti.
    25 Oct. 1949 - ALS Describes current conditions of author's life and mentions projected biography of Swinburne.
    27 Oct. 1949 - ALS Discusses current financial situation of author and mentions grant recently received by her.
    1953 - Signed Card. Mentions Hillyer's experience at Kenyon College and comments on young American poets and authors met in Rome.
    2 Oct. 1953 - ALS Describes author's "writing block" and describes meeting with daughters of Rossetti and mistress and daughter of Ezra Pound; author comments on Pound's poetry in favorable tone. Congratulates Hillyer on his marriage.
- Family correspondence
  Permission to read family correspondence (Box 6) must be granted by Laura V. (Mrs. Stanley H.) Hillyer; upon her death, permission must be granted by either of her two daughters, Elizabeth V. Hillyer or Francesca P. Hillyer. Mrs. Hillyer is also to be contacted when anyone is interested in the scholarly use of Robert Hillyer's works and papers.
  - Hillyer, Mrs. James Rankin, 1906-1930 (Box 6)
    This maternal correspondence consists of 32 ALS written between 1906 and 1930 of which 7 are undated. They are written from Edgarstown, Massachusetts; East Orange, New Jersey; and West Hampton, New York, to Hillyer at Kent School, Harvard University, Tours and Paris, France. The unsuccessful efforts of Hillyer's mother to publish his non-martial prose and poems during the First World War are mentioned. There are comments on Hillyer's pending commission to First Lieutenant. The war-time atmosphere prevailing in America is described as is the national acclaim of Lindbergh. Opinions on equal rights for women are given. The possibility of Hillyer remaining in France at the Sorbonne is discussed.
  - Smith, Marion Couthouy, 1914-1930 (Box 6)
    Correspondence from Hillyer's aunt consists of 12 ALS, written between 1914 and 1930, 1 typed verse with holograph addendum and 1 holograph verse which is undated. Written from New York City, Rye Beach, New Hampshire, and East Orange, New Jersey, they were received in Pomfret, Connecticut, and France. The author, also a poet, frequently discussed problems of writing and publication, and criticized various poems of Hillyer's.
  - Smith, E. O., 1919-1926 (Box 6)
    Correspondence from Hillyer's uncle consists of 4 ALS written between 1919 and 1926 and one undated poem, holograph signed. They were written from East Orange, New Jersey, 419 West 118th Street, New York City, to Paris and Pomfret, Connecticut. Hillyer's poems are very favorably compared to those of his aunt, Marion Couthouy Smith, and his marriage to Dorothy Hancock Tilton is commented on.
  - Marsh, Lillian Hillyer, 1906; undated (Box 6)
    Correspondence of sister consists of 4 ALS, one dated 1906, the other two undated and 1 telegram. They contain general family news.
  - Medina, Ethel Hillyer, 1951-1954; undated (Box 6)
    Correspondence of sister consists of 4 ALS of which one is undated and the others written between 1951 and 1954. They contain certain general family news.
  - Hillyer, H. Stanley, 1954 (Box 6)
    Correspondence of brother dated 1954. Two letters written from New York City to Delaware. They contain general family news and an interesting comment on family genealogy.
  - Medina, Judge Harold R., 1953-1961 (Box 6)
    Correspondence of brother-in-law consists of 12 TLS dated 1953 and 1961 and carbon copy of 1 TLS to a third person, dated November 14, 1960. Author comments on his law practice and occasionally aids Hillyer. There are frequent appreciations of Hillyers poetry and mentions of the author’s projected writing plans.
  - Hillyer, Stanley H., 1936-1961 (Box 6)
    Correspondence of son consists of 319 ALS, 19 Signed Cards, and 20 Telegrams. Dated 1936 to 1961, there is childhood correspondence which internal evidence indicates precedes that date. These were written from Pomfret, Connecticut, Exeter, New Hampshire, Jaffrey, New Hampshire, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Pass Christian, Mississippi, New Orleans, Louisiana, Auckland, New Zealand, Mexico and Europe to New York City, Cambridge, Massachusetts, Greenwich, Connecticut, Gambier, Ohio, California, Delaware, St. Johns, V. I., and Pomfret, Connecticut. Various problems of school life are discussed and curriculum and general conditions are described at length. The relationships between Hillyer, his son, and his wife are commented upon, frequently.
  - Hillyer, Stanley H., 1961-1962 (Box 6)
    Correspondence consists of 7 ALS to Mrs. Jeanne Hillyer written about 1961 and 1962. They are written from Boston, Massachusetts, and Milan, Italy, to Delaware. Arrangements surrounding the death of Robert S. Hillyer are mentioned.
  - Hillyer, Jeanne, 1953-1957 (Box 6)
    Correspondence consists of 10 ALS, 1 marriage announcement, and 1 birthday card written from various locations by Mrs. Jeanne Hillyer to Robert Hillyer, Stanley Hillyer, Ethel Hillyer Medina, and Lillian Hillyer Marsh. This is personal correspondence concerning family problems and events.
- Outgoing correspondence
  - Folder 1 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of 29 ALS, 17 TLS, 1 cable, 1 menu, 1 group of sonnets, and a diary-like letter entitled in Hillyer's hand "Letters of an Ambulancier" dated 1917-1919. These were written from Cambridge, Massachusetts, on board ship en route to France, and from several sections of France to Hillyer's mother, Mrs. James Rankin Hillyer in East Orange, New Jersey. Hillyer announces decision to leave Harvard and join the American Ambulance Corps, his mother accedes and Hillyer's preparations for the trip are described. The trip over is described in detail along with various events taking place in Paris. Hillyer comments on the organization of the ambulance services and gives his impression of the atmosphere of Paris. French attitudes towards the war are noted and analyzed. The French government finally assigns Hillyer and his old friend and ambulance companion, Frederick van den Arend, to the front where they are in the same unit as John Dos Passos, Dudley Poore, and other Harvard men. Hillyer gives elaborate descriptions of living quarters, food service, the conditions of the towns he Sees, the bombing raids, and the actual business of transporting wounded men. Graphic descriptions of the battle fields and the fortifications are given, along with comments on the "Poilu" (French fighting men). A brief description of the general reaction to the Armistice is followed by descriptions of Hillyer's activities as a courier for The American Commission for Peace. Hillyer comments on pacifism, war, conscription, and gas warfare.
  - Folder 2 (Box 7)
    Correspondence consists of typescript Copies of the letters mentioned in folder 1.
  - Folder 3 (Box 7)